one moment sorry got up
yeah I need to adjust my seat or with my
Clark's
assistance I think it we've done it is
somebody very tall must been sitting
here
last I'm sorry yes
uh have we had it called on or you have
sorry I didn't notice
um yes Miss y my lords um I appear for
the appellant credential Assurance
Company Limited and my learnning friend
Mr mantle appears for the respondent
Commissioners could I just check that
your Lordships should have three bundles
in front of you um a core bundle a
supplementary bundle and an authorities
B we do thank
you so this is credentials appeal from a
decision of the upper tribunal um and it
concerns whether that value added tax
should be charged to A supplier called
Silver Fleet on Services provided when
silver Fleet and the recipient of those
supplies credential the apparent were
members of the same thatat
group and we say it shouldn't the first
year tribunal agreed but the upper
tribunal then overturned um the first
year tribunal decision and found that
that was chargeable because the Services
were in part invoice and paid for after
silver Fleet had left the vtic gr yes M
we we have of course um read it quite
carefully and indeed the the facts um
you've really said all that needs to be
said already um we Su slightly to our
surprise that um although apparently two
two days in the upper tribunal it's
dropped another two days here um we may
be turn out to be surprised but we don't
think this really needs to be a two-day
case we wouldn't be surprised if it
finished today and even if it didn't
finish today I don't think it'll go the
whole of Tomorrow My Lord so um you can
take it we've read it and given it some
thought so um you can be relatively
focused in your introductory remarks
my um so we say this appeal was about
how you construe section 43 subsection
one of the V act and in light of the
fact that it's the UK's implementation
of article 11 of the principle that
directive and that directs member states
when they Implement a v grouping regime
to treat the members of that group as a
single taxable
person um and it's about whether when
you have a transaction a real life
transaction between one member of a vat
group and another member that gives rise
to any vat
consequence we say not three principal
reasons because you disregard the
transaction section 43 sub one sub a
tells you um also because you recognized
that silver Fleet is not a taxable
person and also because you recognize
will you treat the business of silver
Fleet as carried on by the
representative member just
credential we say you do that because it
is required by section 43 sub one and it
is necessary to give effect to the
legislative purpose of treating silver
Fleet and credential as a single taxable
person whilst they're members of the
same bat
group The Commissioners in contrast they
invite you to lift that transaction out
of the vat group to allow it to have
that consequences as if it were a
transaction between non-grouped
independent taxable
persons in this way the commissioner
saying that the time of Supply rule in
regulation 90 is engaged and that gives
rise to a v liability of silver fee
we say that's wrong because the starting
point of that analysis is to not regard
not recognize the reality that when
these transactions actually took place
the Investment Management Services were
provided silver Fleet and credential
were to be treated as a single taxable
person because they were back grouped uh
we say that's the commissioner's case is
against the purpose of reading of the
legislation against the body of case La
both European and domestic
um the facts I won't take your law ships
through them um they're pretty simple
when were summed up but um they are in
the first year tribunal's Judgment of
paragraphs 4 to 12 um essentially silver
Fleet provided certain I said we do know
the facts yeah
great um then I'll move on to the
legislation if we could start at least
in Tab four of the
authorities
and look at so on page 29 starting at
the bottom is article two of the
principle of that
Direct in paragraph one begins the
following transaction shall subject to
that if you turn over the page um what
will see the supply of services for
consideration within the territory of
the member state by a taxable person
acting as
such and that provision is implemented
in the domestic legislation in section
one of the vat act um my lords I'm
afraid I'll be flipping for a while
between tabs one and four just so I can
show you is that necessary um nobody's
suggesting that
any real light is thrown on the meeting
room the domestic statute by the
directive or is it are they certainly
when it comes to how you construe
section 43 in the domestic legislation
right I will I I and take that in proper
very well so if we flip to uh tab
one page
three section one sub one sub a of the
that act um value add tax shall be
charged in accordance with the
provisions of this act on the supply of
goods or services in the United Kingdom
including anything treated as a supply
and then over the page section four of
the vat act um scope of VAT on taxable
supplies subsection one vat shall be
charged on any supply of goods or
services made in the United Kingdom
where it is a taxable Supply made by a
taxable person in the course of furance
of any business carried on by him by the
taxable person making the
supply um definition of taxable person
then takes so I can take you to the
principal ACT direcor first and tab four
again page
31 that's article 9 paragraph one
taxable person shall mean any person who
independently carries out in any place
any economic activity whatever the
purpose or result of that
activity um that's implemented a
domestic legislation in section three of
the vat act um you don't have that um my
lords in your bundle so if I could hand
up three
copies all the legislation you have
before you are diversions in Force at
the time silver Fleet left the
Vatican
so section three we're doing this
another time could you hold punch it
apologies SE one a person is a taxable
person for the purposes of this act
while he is or required to be registered
under this act so that's the domestic
definition
tax
then we have um what is meant by a
supply of
services um that is in article
24 for the purpose of principal act
directive which is tab for page
32 uh paragraph one supply of services
shall mean any transaction which does
not constitute a supply of
goods and then article 25 a supply of
services May consist inia in one of the
following transactions May the
assignment of intangible property
whether or not subject of the document
establish in title I don't need to read
it that it's see you want us know or
performance cles indeed my Lord um but
the point is a supply is a transaction
which we say is a real world
event and you see that reflected in the
UK legislation um section five of the
vat act which is tab one page
five so sorry page
five meaning of Supply um subsection One
schedule 4 shall apply for determining
which be treated supply of goods for
services um subsection two subject any
provisions made by that schedule and to
the treasury order orders under
subsection 3 to 6 below a Supply in this
act shall include all forms of Supply
but not anything done otherwise then for
a consideration and B anything that is
not a supply of goods but done for a
consideration including if so done the
granting assignment or Surrender of any
right is a supply of so a supply is
something that is done it's some event
that has happened in real
life and then the
next c um is is article 11 which sets
out the bat grouping
regime Tab four par page
31 to article 11 of the
principal page 31 after Consulting the
advisory committee on value added tax
their office of that committee each
member state may regard as a single
taxable person and any persons
established in the territory of that
member State who while legally
independent are closely bound to one
another by Financial economic and
organizational links there's
no doubt in this case that um silver
Fleet and and credential at the relevant
time uh were closely Bound in a relevant
way um but as article 11 says one
regards as a single taxable person those
who are that grouped and then a member
State exercising the option provided for
in the first paragraph
May adopt any measure needed to prevent
tax evation avoidance through the use of
this provision and there's no suggestion
in this case that there is any tax
avoidance so article 11 um gives member
State a choice whether to implement in
that Gren regime um the UK has chosen to
do so um and the domestic legislation is
section
43 which is tab one page
subsection one where under sections 43 a
to 43d anybody's corporate are treated
as members of a group any business
carried on by a member of the group
shall be treated as carried on by the
representative member and a any supply
of goods or services by a member of the
group to another member of the group
shall be disregarded will be any Supply
which is a supply to which paragraph a
above does not apply and is a supply of
goods or services by or to a member of
the group shall be treated as a supply
by or to the representative member we
don't need to read any
further A and B are really simply
spelling out the consequences of the
general Point made in the introductory
words A and B spell out um the
consequence it's as if you read and
therefore
and and and therefore indeed because if
one is treated one is treating members
as a single taxable person then of
course internal
transactions of that consequence are
disregarded um and transactions with
third parties are treated as being made
to or by the representative
member as the simple taxable
person and then if I could take you to
um article 193 of the principal of that
directive back to Tab four page
36 that's the last page in the
tab provid for the obligation to
pay um article 193 that shall be payable
by any taxable person carrying out a
taxable supply of goods or Serv Services
except where it is payable by another
person in case of virtue articles4 to9
not and then flip forward if you could
um a couple pages to page
34 those are Provisions setting out what
triggers the liability to that and one
back becomes
chargeable so starting in article 62 for
the purposes of this directive one
chargeable event shall mean the
occurrence by virtue of which the legal
conditions necessary for that to become
chargeable are
fulfilled and two that shall become
chargeable when the tax Authority
becomes entitled under the law at a
given moment to claim the tax from the
person liable to pay even though the
time of payment may be deferred so there
you see the distinction being drawn
between the chargeable event which An
Occurrence a real life event that
satisfies the legal conditions necessary
for that to become chargeable and then
paragraph two um is about timing when
the tax Authority becomes
entitled to claim the tax for the person
that's when tax becomes
chargeable and article
article 63 the chargeable event shall
occur and that shall become chargeable
when the goods or services are supplied
so that's the primary facy Rule and then
article 64 and
65 set out certain um special cases so
64 when it gives rise to successive
statements of account or successive
payments supply of goods other than that
consisting of high of goods Etc in the
third terms um all the supply of
services shall be regarded as being
completed on the expiry of the period
toos account of payment
relate member states May provide in
certain cases The Continuous supply of
services over a period of time is to be
regarded as completed at least at
intervals of one
year article 65 where a payment is to be
made on account before goods or services
are supplied that shall become
chargeable on the rece payment and all
the amount received and then article
66 um by way of derogation from article
63 64 and
65 member states May provide that V
Institute become chargeable in respect
of certain transactions or certain
categories of taxable persons at one of
the following times a no later than the
time the invoice is issued B no later
than the time of payment is received and
C where an invoice is not issued ued or
is issued late within a specified period
from the date of the chargeable event so
what you see from article 66 um and and
this is the article um which is
implemented in the UK by regulation
90 so what you see from article 66 is
you need a transaction in order for any
that to become chargeable member states
May provide for that to be chargeable in
respect of certain
transactions the timing rule say relates
only to when that becomes chargeable and
article
66 what it does not do is change the
date of the
transaction you still need a chargeable
event a transaction that amounts to a
chargeable event for the purpose of
article
62 and the fact and timing of that
transaction of that chargeable event are
not changed by article
and then what I need to show you is how
the timing Provisions implemented in
domestic legislation so if we could
start um back in tab one
page
uh section one sub two the that
act that on any supply of goods or
services is a liability of the person
making the supply and subject to
Provisions about accounting and payment
become due at the time of
Supply so the time of Supply rules
affect when that becomes
due
we say that's when it becomes chargeable
consistent with article 66 of the
principle of that
directive and then section six is the
time of Supply provision that's on page
seven subsection one the provisions of
the section shall apply subject to sorry
where we drawn to Sor is Page seven in
tab
one section six of the vat act time of
Supply subsection one the provisions of
this section shall apply subject to
sections 18 18 B and 18 c which are not
relevant for determining the time when a
supply of goods or services is to be
treated as taking place for the purpose
of the charge to
bat and in subsection three subject to
subsections 4 to 14 below the supply of
services shall be treated as taking
place at the time when the services are
performed if you turn over the page page
eight um subsection 14 about 2third of
the way down that page the Commissioners
May by regulations make Provisions with
respect to the time at which not
standing sub sections 2 to8 and 11 to 13
above in section 55 a supply is to be
treated as taking place in cases where
um a it is a supply of goods or services
for a consideration the whole or part of
which is determined or payable
periodically or from time to time or at
the end of any
period uh and then the last part of
subsection 14 at the bottom of the page
and for any such cases as mentioned in
this subsection the regulations you
provide for goods or services to be
treated as separately and successively
supplied at prescribed time or
intervals and that's the
provision regulation 90 the timing law
in our case is enacted that's behind tab
two on page
24 regulation 90 of the 1995 uh value
added tax
regulations subsection one subject to
paragraph two loans where Services
except those to which regulation three
applies relevant where services are
supplied for a period for a
consideration the whole or part which is
determined or payable periodically or
from time to time it shall be treated as
separately and successively supplied at
the earlier of the following times a
each time that a payment in respect of
the supplies is received by the supplier
will be each time the supplier issues a
vatting point relating to the
supplies so looking at the first part
subsection one um where services are
supplied apped for a period Etc um that
must be a reference to the real world
Supply or
transaction it's only where you have a
real world
transaction that you engage regulation
where they are
supplied so that is all that all the
legislation I need to take you to for
now
um if we take a look um at the first
year tribunal's decision
below that's in your PO
bundles
10 the last tab not quite the last tab
tab
if your Shi could please go to page 133
of the
bundle so the first year tribunal quite
rightly we say um
followed the decision in BJ rice which I
will take you to um as re to judgement
VI course but paragraph
34 of the first year tribunal's judgment
um both parties refer to a number of
authorities in supporting the position
one of the earliest is the decision of
the court of appeal in BJ
rice and then the facts the taxpayer in
BJ rice has supplied tax consultancy if
you're going to read a long CH it's easy
for us to read to ourselves how much of
this were you going to read uh if you
could please um my Lord read to the end
of paragraph 36 over the
page
for
sorry just as a matter of trivia for a
non- tax specialist obviously
no QC why does he say as he then was
what did he
become he became a tribunal judge he was
oh I see I didn't realize that he became
thir Steven Oliver didn't he which maybe
what Mr gamy had in mind I see thank you
very good for my education and one
indeed um and after that if I could
please invite you to turn to page 141 in
the same
tab
and please read to yourselves um
paragraphs 70 through to 77 over the
page that's still in the so you want to
read the whole of 7 to 77 70 to 77 yes
we obviously have read
that this perhaps as well we read it
again
that's
it's fair to say isn't it that some
essentially you can see arguments both
ways on the statut construction but um
he thought that they were
authoritatively um resolved by rice his
ratio really was he was following rice
indeed the the ftt found um against
credential um we say wrongly
um on the on the proposition that you
could was right to apply regulation 90
in this case to establish a time of
Supply um at the point of invoice and
payment which will post group we say
that was wrong but nevertheless um the
TT held um on the principles established
in BJ rice that nevertheless was did not
generate any B liability of silver Fleet
because silver fleet was not making the
supplies in the course of furtherance
for business carried on by it its
business was treat carried on by
presedential so just to understand Mr
game's reasoning aside from the
reference to Rice he seems to be focused
particularly on the opening words of
section 43 rather than the disregard uh
indeed he he's he's focusing on the the
opening words of section 43 where it
says you treat the business of
paraphrasing members of the group as
carried on by the
recent
yes and the ft's decision was overturned
by the upper
tribunal its decision is in the core
bindle behind tab
six page
99 Parra 114
summarizes their
reasoning
so paragraph 114 bottom of page 99 it
says in reaching his decision we
conclude the FDT made the following
errors of the
law
one the F
correctly was not a m approv time the
supply was not subject to the disregard
that's by disregard he means the
provision in section 43 sub one
Suba providing for supplies made by one
member of the group to another to be
disregarded so that's what he means by
disregard it ER in law in not app find
same analysis and conclusion in respect
of the Assumption by the Assumption the
upper tribunal means um the statutory
requirement to treat the business
carried on by silver Fleet during the
group period as carried on by
presedential as a representative member
Tri means by the
Assumption the services were not assumed
by virtue of section 43 sub to be
supplied by credential because they were
supplied which took place in
20156 20156 was when batting voices were
raised and payments made um we did not
argue that the services were supplied by
presedential we don't say they were
supplied by we say that the business of
silver Fleet at the time suppes the
transactions took place the supplies
were actually made um the business of
silver fleet was treated to be as
carried on by
credential we don't say section 43 St
one doesn't say it's treated
a and paragraph two um the Ft expressed
concern um at mixing the real world with
the vat world to create a tax charge but
approach makx the real world and the Bat
World in order to avoid a bat charge it
took Services which in the real world
were rendered by silver Fleet in the
course of its business and apply to them
a vat World treatment in which silver
fleet's business was assumed to be
carried
onti three was a material error of law
to regard the position of silver Fleet
as being indistinguishable from that of
Mr rice silver fleet was not entirely
outside the scope of that when the
services were rendered but rather was
subject to a specific set of assumptions
and dis s the FDT therefore Ed in
regarding itself as Bound by BJ rice to
allow potential
appeal and then finally four since none
of the decided cases provided direct
Authority for the issue in the appeal
and the FD should have given weight to
the comments of Lord hofman Lady Justice
Arden and Lord Walker in deciding
whether to extend the approach adopted
by the court of appeal and BJ rice and
just noting that um the judgments of
Lord Hoffman and Lady Justice are to
which that paragraph refers um Lord
hofman in s materials the Justice Arden
in RSA were both dissenting
judgments yes although it's set out in
Four
Points it's really a single point
on the construction of the relevant
provisions and the approach which they
enjoyed
um follow
by saying why the
authorities
uh didn't require the FDT to take a
different
approach indeed the distinguishing BJ
rice from from the case before the
tribunal essentially on the basis and
you see that in
um three um so the upper tribunal
considered that it was
um decisive that Mr rice was not
required to be registered for that at
the time the supplies were in fact made
so that he was um outside entirely theb
entirely outside the scope of that as we
will see and I'll take you to um a
decision of the
cju at the time the Investment
Management Services were in fact
provided by silver Fleet silver Fleet
could not be treated as a taxable person
it was not a taxable person it was not
permitted well taod and Trail a
submission you'll make it into du
course yes so we've looked at the two
decisions um so we say that the upper
tribunal was wrong essentially in the
following three ways um first um ering
law in holding that um when a
transaction
an event An Occurrence that might
provide produce supplying when a
transaction takes place between members
of the same V group and the upper
tribunal said wrongly we say that
regulation 90 applies to determine
whether that transaction gives rise to a
supply at a particular time and it is
that that determines
taxability we say that on the purpose of
construction of the legislation the
transaction taking Place between members
of the same bat group is
disregarded so there is no Supply to
which regulation
19 alternatively even alternative this
your point two uh this is sort of one
sub
two what was sub one sub one is set on a
purpose of construction when you have a
transaction taking place between members
of the same that group you don't get
okay it's fine I just wasn't sure what
the structure of submission was
alternatively yeah alternatively um even
if it were right to apply regulation 90
um that cannot make taxable which was
something that was not a taxable Supply
at the time the transaction took place
and that's because silver fleet was not
then a taxable
person the only taxable person being
credential as a representative member
and that's the BJ
rice yeah and then the second
second is that the upper tribunal on
ering in in failing to recognize it even
if one could apply regulation
19 no V liability can arise to Silver
Fleet because the supply was not made in
the c or furtherance of a business that
silver fleet was carrying
on regulation 90 in a timing rule does
not change the business in the course or
furtherance of which a supply was made
nor does it change the identity of the
person carrying on that business which
in this case was presedential as the
representative
member and then the third error of law
um that the other tribunal made we say
is in holding that this case does not
concern the consequence of that
grouping um and in so doing um the upper
tribunal therefore wrongly failed to
take into account a number of relevant
European and domestic authorities that
I'll take you to
essentially its error is in failing to
give effect to the reality that silver
Fleet and credential were members of the
same vat
group when the transactions took place
you making this over
complicated these are three separate
consequences of a
single
issue which is whether as a matter of
construction
uh the uh timing rules in regulation
apply to section
43 um isn't that on once if you're
if you're submitting on that is right
all these are just consequences of
that if you're wrong about that that
solves all the problems raised by all
three of your points it's essentially
two points um my Lord um first of all
whether regulation 90 applies at
all1 because if you are disregarding
transactions would say you should made
between group member silver Fleet to
credential then you don't have services
that are supplied when you come to look
at regulation 19 which is a prerequisite
for applying that regulation so you
don't get to apply regulation
19 do you apply section 43 first I mean
in the real world Services were supplied
by silver Fleet to credential for
consideration in the real world
transactions took place between silver
Fleet and credential at a time when they
were members of the same bat group and
needed to be treated as a single taxable
person but you've jumped ahead my
question was you say you apply section
43 first before you apply regulation 90
and I think your answer indicates that
you your submission does say that you
you start with the real world in which
there was a transaction under which
Services were
supplied by silver Fleet to the
credential who were to dependent
businesses with their own businesses in
the real
world you say before you get to a time
of Supply rules you next go to section
43 take account of the fact they were in
the same P group therefore that real
world
transaction in fact applied in the
course of silver fet's own business to
the credential is disregarded and
treated as if it didn't take place for
the at purposes so you never get
regulation indeed you you recognize the
reality that when those transactions
took place the two entities were that
grouped section 43 yes you say that's a
reality the consequence that it's
treated as it's deemed not to be a
transaction it's disregarded for vat
purposes is a vat consequence and you
say you apply that consequence before
you get to regulation
19 you do my understanding is that the
revenue's position
is do it the other way around you first
say there's a real world transaction for
consideration regulation 90 tells you
when it took place it took place in part
when you were members of the same V
group that's disregarded and in part
when you weren't members of the same V
group and that's
vable that's the commissioner's position
yes yeah does it not come down to which
you apply first I mean the ARB at one
point said it's a chicken and egg
situation is that not the question we
have to
it one can one can one can think of it
as which do you apply first but really
it's a question of how do you construe
section
43 and the requirement to treat silver
Fleet and credential when the
transactions in fact took place as a
single taxable person but that but the
answer to that depends on which you take
first you can't well if you had a single
entity with say two
branches and one was providing Services
one branch was providing services to the
other
Branch um there is then a demerger at a
later point and you end up with two
companies um one keeps the benefit of
the services in exchange for making
payments to the other
entity there would be no question and I
don't think the Commissioners would
argue otherwise that there would be any
of that consequence because even though
you have payments taking place after the
Dem merger
there was no Supply the the services
were provided by one branch to another
within the same entity So when you say
payments you merely
mean accounting entries within one
company no my Lord um sorry I haven't
explained myself branches do you mean
separate corporate entities or do when
when they've Dem merged I thought by
merger and Dem merger you meant a
splitting of a single corporate entity
you start with a single corporate
entity with two branches yes so they are
not legally separate persons or branches
legally separate persons no not legally
that stage it would just be internal
accounting entries in internal provision
of services um so one Department
provides certain services to another
department helpful because I'm sure
you're right but I mean so what single
taxable person my Lord this is how
you're meant to treat members of a v
group as a single taxable person so when
silver Fleet in fact provided the
services too credential they were
members of the same V group yes and we
say you treat them yes as as the case
law you deem them contrary to reality
contrary to reality contrary to reality
but it's a necessary deeming because um
that is what you must do if you've at
group um if if a member State implements
the V grouping regime so you treat them
as a single taxable
person similar to divisions of the same
yeah entity then if at a later
point that entity Dem merges into two
separate companies to distinct legal
persons two separ it isn't quite the
same because it's merely within a
company
um there's no real transaction at all
it's just an accounting entry as between
yes two divisions precisely and that is
what the disregard in section 43 tells
you to do you you do disregard what in
fact took place between silver Fleet and
credential because they were that
grouped but in the case of two two
branches within a single corporate
entity there is no supply for
consideration and and indeed there is no
supply for that purposes a supply for
consideration in our case well there is
well right but that clearly is in the
real world these are two companies real
money will real services will pass from
company one to company two and real
consideration will pass from Company 2
to company one um depending how
meticulous they are in principle one
will have invoiced the other and it is
also part of that reality that when all
that when the when the transactions take
place the two are V grouped that is also
part of the reality is that they were
vat
grouped they were vat grouped they were
members of the same vat Group Well you
say that's a reality it's not a reality
it's a it's a legal fiction well or are
the consequences of them being back
grouped is a legal fiction the
consequences may follow the legal
Provisions but that the two were members
of the same vat group is a
reality and from that
reality flows the
consequences one of which is that well
the mo the the only one consequence
really which is you treat all the
members of that that group as a single
taxable person at that
time and really what that means is that
you treat the transactions that in fact
took place between silver Fleet and
credential as something that took place
within a single taxable person it has no
that consequence and that's what section
43 sub one Suba means by you disregard
those yes in circumstances where it
applies in circumstances where depends
on the timing of the supply it's
unfortunate perhaps that the that
section 43 sub one Suba uses the word
Supply um which is liable to generate
confusion but it cannot be right we
say in this
case for a that consequence to
arise from what Happ what took place
between silver Fleet and credential when
the two were that
grouped
because you could only
get a v charge on Silver Fleet if you
give that consequence to what you allow
what took place between silver Fleet and
credential during a period when they
were members of the same vat group you
allow that to have vat consequence and
that that goes against a treatment of
all the members of that bat group at
that time as a single taxable person
things that take place within a single
taxable person should not be giving rise
to that
consequences but what the Commissioners
say and what the upper tribunal said is
that you have to lift those transactions
out of the vat
group and give them that
consequence that's rather tendentious
way of putting
it say that they don't fall within the V
group um because of the timing of the
relevant Supply so it's not lifting I
mean depends who's right whether
you indeed they do they do say that but
in order to do that you have to apply
regulation 90 and regulation 90 as we
saw says where services are supplied for
a period for consideration
Etc when you have transactions taking
place within a v group
services are disregarded
and it is not really a chicken and egg
situation when you think of it when when
you bear in mind that section 43 must be
construed so as to be compatible with
article 11 that's my le thing i' only to
take you there it's it's in your bundle
paragraph um authorities tab 17 as mying
but it can't be controversial that you
canr section 43 so as to be compatible
with the purpose of article 11 of the
principle of that directive
can I just talk around that for one
moment um as I understand it when you
look at the reason for article
11 you find it's about administrative
convenience really there's no policy of
giving an
exemption uh it was thought to be
administratively convenient within a
group uh and of course if everybody's ta
everybody's supplying vable Services
it's tax neutral anyway because the re
recipient of the services will recover
as input tax whatever it would have paid
to the other member of the
group so so the policy is Administrative
convenience while you're members of a
group now why does that
policy say that you should win in
construing section 43 why does the
administrative convenience continue to
apply once you've left the
group well um the purpose of article 11
has been considered in
um a couple of European cases that
perhaps will be convenient me to take
you to um now but merly to say this
which is it must form part um of
administrative
convenience that you do not
need to have regard for V purposes to
anything that takes place inside a
group and what the Commissioners are
arguing for in this
case is that you do have regard to what
took place inside a vat
group to is you changed your tense
there you say that you shouldn't have
regard to anything that takes place
within a group and then you say the
Commissioners say that you shouldn't
have regard to things that took place uh
so we're now dealing with something
that is happening when it's no longer
part of the group namely the payment
that's that that that's because I
changed my T because when you come to
look at regulation 90 you're looking at
a later time which is when the invoices
are raised and payments are
made but perhaps it's convenient for me
to take you to those um European cases
um let's star in Commission in Ireland
which is authorities fund tab
19 about the Irish
um it admitted um about grouping where
at least one of the members was a
taxable person and and they were Bound
in the relevant way the European
commission took the view that in so far
as it permitted non-taxable persons to
be members of the vat group and the
Irish legislation was
incompatible with articles 9 and 11 of
the princip
direct
um held that um it wasn't Apparent from
article 11 that non- taxal persons could
not be included in a V
group um if I could please ask you to
turn to page
307 this is in um Advocate General
yasin's opinion
paragraph 28 the Afric Journal says at
the outset it's useful to recall that
according to the settled case law of the
court in determining the meaning of the
provision of European Union law its
objectives context and wording must all
be taken into account I'll first
consider the wording of article 11 in
light history before examining its
context and
objectives um then at D in the margin
start of legislative history and
wording go through it um and then on
page
308 paragraph 36 that includes therefore
article 11 of the vat directive allows
member states to regard as a single
taxable person any legally independent
persons established with the territory
of the M state provided they are closely
found to one another by Financial
economic and organizational links uh
this conclusion is in Conformity with
the principle of legal certainty which
is particularly important in taxation
matters where not only only taxable
persons and taxx authorities but also
the member states need to rely on the
clear and precise ating of the residance
of the European Union and then he he
dismisses the commission the
commission's
argument what was what was the question
the question was whether um the
principal vat directive permitted non-
taxable person someone who wasn't a
taxable person to be a member of a vat
group commission said you couldn't do
that that the European Court said you
could permit non- taxable persons to be
members for
that thank
you um and
then point B of the opinion the E
General goes on to consider the
objective and context of the that
grouping
Provisions over the page page
309 paragraph 39 do we not need to Nace
paragraph
38 paragraph 38 um the explanatory
memorandum indeed for the proposal to
the proposal for the six back directive
states in the interest of simplifying
administration of combating abuses EG
the splitting of one economic operator
among several taxable persons so that
each May benefit from a special scheme
that member states will not be obliged
to treat as a taxable person those whose
Independence is purely a legal
technicality the legislative history of
the provision establishing that groups
reveal no other aims the commission
those goals preclude the inclusion of
non-taxable persons in the vat
group and then 39 in order to understand
the purpose of vat grouping within the
context of the broader vat regime
account needs to be taken of the effect
vat groups have on fiscal neutrality
this entails consideration of the
Practical effects of registering a v
group this is significant because these
effects May well provide the motivation
for economic operators to be involved in
V provided that they have a choice in
this respect under the applicable
National
legislation and then C the vat grouping
option in the broader context of V reg
of the V
reg uh the forming of a v group results
in the creation of a single how much do
you want us to read here um if you could
please um my Lord read um paragraphs 40
through to to the end of
42 uh and then on page
310 If You Could Read um from D well the
sideline Seline yes
well
second
for
yes so just points to emphasize um
creation of single taxable person that
is in all respects comparable to a
taxable person consisting of only one
entity that's paragraph 40 um that is
consequence of that grouping
um paragraph 42 the establishment of AD
group initiates the vat liability of the
vat group and terminates the separate
tax liability of those of its members
who were taxable persons for V purposes
before joining the
group
um and at the end the last sentence or
sorry theultimate sentence paragraph 42
transactions transactions between
individual members of the group and
which remain therefore within the group
are considered to have been carried out
by the group for itself consequently a
that group's internal transactions do
not exist
for that purposes if you refer back um
to article 66 of the principal V
directive which which gave member states
how to enact
timings that's Tab
four page
45 by way of derogation from article 63
64 65 member states May provided that
that is to become chargeable in respect
of certain
transactions Etc no later than the time
of the invoice or payment but you need a
transaction and what the ad General is
saying here is that of that group's
internal transactions do not
exist doesn't this come up against the
same question which I've been suggesting
to you as the only real question which
is uh does the uh group regime apply to
this particular transaction
at the relevant time yes and we we say
it does because when they're talking
about transaction they're talking about
what happened in in the world the actual
performance of the services by silver
Fleet to presential which undoubtedly
took place when the two were members of
the same B
group and and I just um make a couple
more points um on the basis of of what
The Advocate General said here um
paragraph 46 um in certain situations
members of a fat group May gain economic
benefits from belonging to the group
this in my opinion simply an inevitable
consequence flowing from the basic
fiscal policy choice of a member state
to permit that
grouping and and just to be clear the
reason why this case matters credential
is that it does not charge VAT on all
its services otherwise it would recover
the input tax did um but um paragraph 49
um uh that liability says can and does
have an impact on the structure and
functioning of business activities vat
grouping allows member states to
diminish an influence of that on the way
economic operators organize themselves
it can do this by reducing the
difference in costs between producing a
service inhouse that's a real life
concept producing a service in-house and
buying it from a dependent supplier with
separate legal personality thus that
grouping supports fiscal neutrality by
enabling appropriate business structures
without negative consequences in terms
of that
liability and at the risk of repeating
myself going back to the example that we
were talking about
earlier a single legal
entity that um where One Division might
provide Investment Management Services
to another division would not expect any
of that consequence to flow from that
from those transactions and and that the
aty general says is what is the same
purpose that grouping is intended to
achieve so when silver Fleet and
credential were members of the same B
group provisions of services by one to
the other should generate no
Ric and then the next case um is just
the next tab over tab 20 I'm sorry to
interrupt my lords uh but um if your
lordship doesn't have Lord Nei doesn't
have already um the Court's um
affirmation of the point he puts my
learned friend before she went to the
island case that is found in the island
case
itself um at page
319 paragraph
47 where the court directly picks up on
this is the grand chamber in V uh yes it
is I think um it picks up uh it didn't
pick up on everything The Advocate
General said but it did pick up on what
your lordship Drew attention to in
paragraph 38 to the AO so that's the
court
statement yes you're going to take us
unless you want to say anything about
that you're going to take us to lentia
uh paragraph 47 um simply confirms as my
learned friend has said that um uh the
grouping regime is intended either in
interest or simplified Administration
with a view to combating abuses
sorry that was paragraph
47 on page
319 I see sorry yes I moved on to the
other case yes with you yeah the next
case is in tab 20
yes won't attempt to pronounce it draw
it lorentia lorentia thank you my
Lord
um so one of the issues in the renter um
is whether the what was then Article 4
sub4 of the sixth directive now article
11 of the principle of that directive um
precluded National legislation which
reserve the right to form a that group
solely to entities with legal
personality and link to the controlling
company of the group in in a
relationship of
subordination um except where those two
requirements constitute measures which
were appr appr necessary in order to
achieve the objective of seeking to
prevent abusive practice or
behavior and also confirm that article
four sub four of the six directive was
not considered have sorry where you're
reading from somewhere but I'm so sorry
I'm simply summ reading from the bottom
of the head note it's on page 322 thank
you okay well we can see that just
reading sub two and
sub y
if I could then um ask you to turn to
page
332 it's the same point that we've seen
made by The Advocate General in Mission
and Ireland paragraph 48 this is The
Advocate General M GOI in
practice since the vat group is regarded
as a single taxable person the entities
forming it do not continue to submit FS
declaration separately or to be
identified within and outside their
groups as taxable persons 49 it follows
that the V group's internal transactions
that is to say transactions infected for
consideration between the constituent
members do not exist in principle for
that
purposes the right to deduct input taxes
will determined not on the basis of
transactions between members of the
group but solely on the basis of the
group's transactions with third
parties and all that's consistent with
what um the commission the European
commission has said um in its
communication on uh the vat grouping
regime that's in the authorities bundle
behind tab
23 um you can see page
374 at the Top This is a communication
from the commission to the council and
the European Parliament on the V proof
option provided by article
um and then page
375 commission sets up the background
and then paragraph down from the top of
that page against this background the
aim of this communication is to explain
the commission's view on how the
provision of article 11 should be
translated into practical Arrangements
was respect ing the basic principles of
community bat
system uh page
376 Ju Just Before You Go
376 if we look at the first three
paragraphs Under The Heading original
objective yes you get what we've seen
earlier
being expanded
slightly the concept was introduced um
in the sixth
directive to allow administrative I
don't need to read all
out so p
376 paragraph
3.2 the main purpose of the that
grouping provision
option if I could ask your Lordships to
read uh section 3.2 um which continues
over the page stop at
3.3
yes so um as the commission says by
joining of that group the group members
of that purposes dissolve itself from
any possible simultaneously existing
legal forms instead becomes part of a
new separate taxable person for that
purposes namely the V
group in other words for that purposes
while silver Fleet and credential were
in in that group
um they were not they were dissolved of
their separate legal forms but they
formed part of a separate taxable person
um and so the transactions in fact
taking place between during that period
can have no that
consequence um and then finally if you
could please turn to page
382 paragraph 3.4.2 talks about
treatment of supplies tool from third
parties um and then last sentence the V
situation of the group and the treatment
of its incoming and outgoing
transactions are fully comparable to
those for taxable person with different
branches and then paragraph 3.3
3.4.3 ingroup supplies um if I could
invite mips to read that paragraph
piece
this is all pretty obvious stuff isn't
it
indeed thought so but when when silver
Fleet and credential were in fact that
grouped um anything that took place
between them during that
period such as the the actual provision
of the Investment Management Services
should have no bad
consequence and indeed my Lord that
should be OB
p
yes um and then um two uh domestic cases
just
confirming what you've just seen
Commission in Ireland at lentia the
first is Taylor Clark which is
authorities tab
13 can see there if you've turn to page
191 couple of pages
in this is the Judgment of Lord BGE um
between read com with Briggs and mans
age so paragraph one an appeal
concerning a claim for repayment of
unduly levied bat in the context of that
group of companies the question is
whether Taylor Clark can be treated as
having made claims for repayment within
the time limit
Etc when another company which was
formerly a member of the V group um and
not Taylor Clark made relevant claim
that was what the case was about
paragraph 2 as I discussed below the
idea of a v group of companies was
introduced simplify the collection of
that by a ignoring Intergroup
transactions and B by treating supplies
by two any member of the group in their
dealings with entities outside the group
as transaction by single taxable person
so the focus there is on on
transactions um and then page 19
six so L there sets out AR 11 starting
at the bottom of
page5 and top of page 196 he says two
points may be made about this provision
first it is permissive there's no
obligation on a member state to
Institute such a regime and secondly is
not prescriptive it does not lay down
template as to how a member state will
treat a group of person as a single tax
person um and my learned friend makes
the point um that there is no obligation
and that it's not prescriptive it's not
um doesn't tell member states exactly
what to do but nevertheless um it ought
to be uncontroversial that the UK having
decided to implement a b grouping regime
um it must be construed so as to be
compatible as so far as possible and it
is possible um to be compatible with the
purpose of article 11 which we've just
seen and then finally just a little bit
at the bottom of page 196 um so
paragraph
202 he talks about Thor materials which
we will come on to very shortly um and
what Lord says
there he says he doesn't consider Lord
Nolan to be talking about the
representative member to be dealing on
behalf of other members of the V group
um section 43 uh says the bottom section
43 is not concerned with Intergroup
legal Arrangements the group members
it's concerned with dealings in relation
to vat with entities outside the vat
group and with hmrc including the
disregard for in groups supplies
relation to the liability to
tax
and then Lloyd's banking which is behind
tab
15 cour repal
decision this case is about you can see
on page
217 which is in Lady Justice Rose's
judgment paragraph
three issues that arise in these appeals
concern to claim back the tax in
situation where the F or services on
which the tax was wrongly levied were
supplied by companies which were at the
time of the supply members of the pat
group formed pursuant UK legislation
implementation of article
11 and then page
219 paragraph
that ship say there a number of
important Decisions by the Cal Justice
Union clarifying the scope and effect of
theat grouping Provisions paragraph 15s
about an scientifica we will come on to
at paragraph 16 she talks about European
Commission of Ireland which we've
seen um paragraph 17 the Judgment of the
CJ began its analysis by recalling that
in determining the meaning of a
provision of U law the objective context
and wording wording of the law must all
be taken into
account over the page paragraph 18 um
the Court's reasoning in Commission in
Ireland followed closely that of
Advocate General yasin's opinion in that
case and we've seen that
opinion
um and then if I could ask you to read
to the um end of paragraph 19 um you'll
have seen the um the quoted part ready
when we went through commission
Ireland yep
so there you have um Lady Justice um
Rose she was at the time
um saying that um what The Advocate
General said in in commission Ireland
and closely followed by the court um by
the court in that case um is
right then uh I don't to read you to
read through it paragraphs um 21 through
to
23 is the lorentia case she makes the
same
point um at paragraph 26 on page
224 um she says she was taken to the
commission communication which we've
also just
seen um and then page
251 please my lords um paragraph
120 paragraph 120 um Lady Justice Rose
says the case laws was inconsistent with
the joint appell and submission of that
grouping provision should not affect the
underlying rights and obligations of
members on the contrary it is a key
feature of the V grouping of that
grouping that where companies come
together to form a group there are
significant changes to the tax treatment
of their supplies it is not simply a
matter of the single taxable person
accounting for the same amount of that
as would have been payable on the
members transaction transactions had
they remained independently taxable
persons as Advocate General yasinan um
said in Commission in Ireland par 42 one
important change is that V group's
internal transactions do not exist for B
purposes this can bring Financial as
well as administrative advantages where
for example a member of the group makes
exempt supplies and can avoid incurring
non-deductible input tax by obtaining
inputs from a fellow group
member important
paragraph
so we say that the case law is clear um
that whilst the bat group is in
existence internal transactions that's
things that are done for consideration
in section five language um between
group members do do not exist for that
purposes and that's the only way one
achieves the objective of article 11
treating the V group as if it were one
entity and and in so doing conferring a
genuine choice to economic operators as
to whether they wish to structure their
transactions to be inhouse in a single
entity or with another entity in the
same that
group
my learned friend makes the point in his
skeleton argument that you can't know
when a transaction took place without
applying the time of Supply
BS but that's simply not the case you
know when a transaction takes place you
just look at the reality we know when
these transactions took place they took
place inside of that group
during a period um before silver fet
left the back you just look at the
facts will that always be the
case if one can identify
transactions that might constitute a
supply and give rise to that
consequences it must always be the case
that one can identify when the actual
transactions took place even if it's
over a peri perod of time when were the
services performed when did the transfer
of ownership take
place well Sor suppose the service
consists
of um effectively a
retainer to supply
advice uh as required and you get paid
for
that let's assume a very pure case where
you don't actually get
paid anymore or if someone does pick up
the phone and ask you for
advice and suppose that is in that
relationship is in that service is uh in
place over um a period during part of
which someone is with one of the
recipients in the group and uh sorry the
suppliers in the group and part it isn't
when would you say the service was
supplied um you'd have to have some sort
of you'd either have to prate or you'd
have to
have
um some deeming provision would you well
you would you would come down to
um section five domestic legis directs
you um you need to decide when something
was done for a consideration when was
that thing done um and it may be that in
that case one needs to look at the
agreement between the parties the
contract right to identify by what is
the thing that is to be done um and and
when that was done and may of course but
how would you apply that to the kind of
situation I put to you um whatever is
done whilst the supplier and recipient
are in the same vat group is
disregarded and whatever is done what is
done under the arrange under the
circumstances I put to you um well it
depends on what the agreement says but
available if if it is making oneself
available yes to receive instructions
for
example um then whilst one is making
oneself available during a period one is
that grouped with the the payer the
recipient um then that is
disregarded it is as if one division of
a single legal entity is making itself
available to do the bidding of another
division entity
um once either the supplier or the
recipient leaves the vat group um it
then becomes a situation where an entity
is doing something for another entity in
the supplier is a taxable person
carrying on a business suppose you were
being paid £100,000 for
this
um what happens when you leave the group
halfway
through
is it is uh the
consideration
is uh paid as I say at the end of the
period is the whole of that
consideration
exempt part of the service will have
been supplied During the period that you
were within the
group exempts are on word I'm using
Loosely it seems to me that that is a
matter of of construction of the
agreement to establish what the
consideration is paid for it's paid for
the your availability throughout the
period it it um again it's a matter of
in my submission um construing looking
at the agreement between the parties and
saying as a matter of what is agreed
between the parties is the 100,000 paid
prata each day we will pay x amount
adding up to 100,000 is it paid in is it
to be divided in up in some other way
but there will be um on looking at the
agreement construing the agreement an
exercise familiar um to the courts um a
way of
establishing um what consideration was
given for things that were done in the
group and what considerations is given
for things that are done outside the
group well I give the example not to
know what the right answer is but just
to
test whether it is in fact necessary in
any regime of this kind to have
Provisions fixing for certain sorts of
ongoing or continuous
Services when they are to be treated as
having been
supplied you say no in the absence of
Provisions you might have one or two
tricky factual situations but there will
always be an answer is that
right there will always be um one can
always establish on the facts whether
something was done inside a group
yes and um I
think no one is arguing in this case
that if silver Fleet had continued to
provide Investment Management Services
to credential um when the two were no
longer members of the same B group
that those transactions should not
potentially have that
consequence next case I'd like to take
you to is Thor materials it's a House of
Lords um case um it's in the authori
bundle behind Tab
S
um Lord Hoffman just so you know when
you're reading um the judgment's Lord
Hoffman Des sented um Lord Nolan gave a
judgment uh with which Lord Brown Wilson
and Lloyd both agreed um that's right at
the beginning on page bottom of page
75 and
um Lord Clyde agreed with the outcome
but gave his own judgment uh towards the
end of the
report on page 76 at the top um speaking
Lord Nolan's
judgment he set out the facts and the
issue um if you could read from a in the
margin down to the paragraph ending
between C and D just the first two
paragraphs
yes so 90% of the price paid um inside
of that group 10% paid outside the
actual transaction took place outside
the group um note there was no argument
in that case that it was right to apply
the timing provision Because the actual
transaction took place outside the V
group nobody was arguing that that had
to be
disregarded question was what does it
mean to disregard the
90% Supply that took place inside the
vat group did it mean you only pay tax
on the 10% on
100 and then if I could ask you to turn
to
page 78
please at the top of page 78 there Lord
Nolan set out the timing Provisions in
that
case just read a through to
C
yeah and then bottom of page 78 um G
through to uh the end of that first
paragraph on page 79 the party's
argument
yeah and then towards the bottom of page
79 you see that article 10 provides so
Lord Nolan setting out article 10 of six
that directive now it's article 62 and
63 of the principle of that directive
we've seen the distinction between
chargeable event and when tax becomes
chargeable and defines when the
chargeable event occurs and when tax
becomes
chargeable then Lord Nolan says at the
bottom of page 79 this article read with
article 5.1 is I think um helpful in
emphasizing the subject of tax liability
is the supply of the goods in the sense
of the transfer of ownership in
them IE the real life occurrence the
thing that is done um in our case the
the actual performance of Investment
Management
Services so the the subject of tax
liability is the supply of the goods in
the sense of the transer ownership in
them which normally occurs as in the
present case at the time of delivery the
article authorized this tax to be
charged by virtue of article
10.2 one transfer of ownership where
it's been a prior payment on account but
that does not displace the necessity for
a transfer ownership to follow in fact
otherwise there will be no chargeable
event and no justification for the
imposition of the tax if I could then
invite your Lordships to read to
continue um from there until the
paragraph the end of parag ending at e
in
margins
yes so the the important part um the
second part of that that paragraph um
coroller for present purposes which
again I Mr bleming to accept
Commissioners in that case um was if the
sequence of events in the present case
being reversed the sale agreement
Advanced payment had taken place before
materials and home became members same
group but the agreement had been
completed after that group any tax
charge on the advanced payment for four
to be refunded um and the important part
the transfer of ownership in the goods
and thus their supply and their supply
would Judy have taken place in reality
yes um but this would have to be
disregarded under Section 29 um that is
now section 43 and so for the purposes
of the charge to tax the chargeable
event anticipated by the charge of tax
upon the advanced payment would have
failed to
materialize in other words an Intergroup
event that is the thing the transaction
that triggers the charge to that um it
takes place Intergroup it's equivalent
to having never taken place and it
cannot you cannot impose the that charge
in those
circumstances we see a number of cases
um in the course of um my submissions
and and that of my Lear friend but this
in my submission is the closest when it
comes to guidance on the very point
before
you
so with that in
mind when you then turn over the page to
page
81 and look at the parts that my learned
friend will invite you to look at um
starting just about B in the margin um
where Lord know says in saying this um I
also accept Mr PR's further submission
that the time of Supply Ro including
Section 5 sub one must be applied to
determine whether and if so when a
supply between members of the same group
took place um it is essential to apply
the time of Supply rules in order to
determine whether the supply took place
while the group relationship still
existed um
Etc um Lord Nolan is very much talking
about what happened in th material
itself which is the the transfer of
ownership the transaction itself took
place outside the bat
group his lordship cannot be talking
about my submission um a situation in
the present case
where the
transaction the supply the transfer of
ownership in Goods or the performance of
the Investment Management Services in
our case actually took place inside of
that group because he had just observed
not three paragraphs earlier that no V
would be due in those
circumstances not withstanding the
application of any timing
rules
and that's the Judgment um of three um
La panel of five then then you've got
starting on page 2 Lord Hoffman's
judgment and bearing in mind it is the
sentent so to the extent what Lord
Hoffman says is
inconsistent with what Lord Nolan and
the majority say
um one ought to take into account uh
what the majority has said and not what
the dissenting judgment
says
I go back to
what page
113 as you
predicted man would rely on what he says
there I can see why you say that because
what he appears to say is you have to
apply time
Supply to determine
whether a supply of two members of the
same group took
place and that seems to be contr to your
submission but you first decid whether a
supply took place only if a supply did
take place you to
supplys it's the term Supply is not
perhaps um particularly helpful um what
what Lord Nolan is saying um in in the
passage um on page
81 um is that when it's on controversial
he must be saying this in light of what
he said three paragraphs earlier um in
light of the fact
that
uncontroversially one has transactions
here taking place outside of that group
then in order to determine whether
anything took place inside of AD group
you have to apply the time of Supply
rules um but
clearly it was his lordship's
view
that even if you apply the time of
Supply rules which he does in his
observation um on page 80 if just been
to does apply the time of Supply rules
because there's a prepayment there um
that has triggered a v charge being
paid but you have to refund it because
the actual transfer of ownership the
transaction that gives rise to the
supply has to be disregarded because it
happened inside of V group between
members
now um my learned friend may make the
point um I believe writing thing he
makes it in his skeleton
argument he says the timing rule in th
materials is different if you look at um
went to it but I didn't read it out it's
on page
78 um it it's what was then section five
sub one says if before the time
applicable under subsection
two the person making the supply issues
the tax invoice in respect of it or if
before the time applicable under
paragraph A or B of subsection to that
section who receives payment um the
supply shall to the extent covered by
the invoice or payment be treated as
taking place at the time the invoice is
issued or the payment is received um and
the Commissioners say ah but this is
different because you you only treat it
is one
Supply um and what happens is that that
um you you only treat a part of it as
being disregarded whereas in our case
it's different because regulation 90
invites you to treat the supply as
separately and successively supplied
each time an invoice or a payment um is
rented or made but there is no
suggestion in the observation of Lord
Nolan on page 80 that had 100% had the
prepayment being of 100% of the price
the outcome would have been any
different
he says in terms
um the transfer of ownership in the
goods and thus their supply would duly
have taken
place but this would have to be
disregarded under Section 29 and so for
the purposes of the charged tax the
chargeable event anticipated by the
charge of tax upon the advanced payment
would have failed to materialize it
could have been a 90% prepayment it
could have been a 50% prepayment it
could have been a 100% prepayment which
under the timing provision would mean
that the whole supply to the extent of
100% is treated as taking place at the
time the invoices issued or payment
received nevertheless Lord Nolan says
you don't have a that charge because you
have to disregard what actually
happened so so the timing the different
timing Provisions is not an
answer
thank
you the
um the next case we need to look at is
um senser which is another house
of decision is the next tab is tab
eight
what happened in
Sensa
um was Sensa um was the UK subsidiary of
a Swedish
Bank um the Swedish bank has also set up
a branch in London to carry out its
business so you had Sensa which was its
own legal entity the subsidiary of the
the bank and then you had London branch
of the
bank Sensa provided certain Management
Services to London
Branch
um at a time when spener and London
Branch were not members of the same V
group they were not permitted to
be at a later point before any invoice
had been rendered or payment made for
those
Services um Sensa and the London Branch
became bad
grouped and the appeal
concerns only the supply that were in
fact made by senska to the London Branch
before they
became
um you see that um just page 94 um at
the top
there last sentence of the sort of half
paragraph the top the issue in this
present case related to the period from
1st of June 1987 to 31st of July 1991
they became backou for the 1 of August
1991 sorry I was keeping up the I'm so
sorry Lord I see yes
yeah so again the facts in
Sensa real world transactions the things
that were done for consideration were
done outside of a bad
group not so in our case
so again there was
no dispute in
Spenser that one could apply the time of
Supply
RS because there was nothing to
disregard in so far far as the actual
transactions were concerned sorry you
you you let your voice drop there was no
issue in spener that that um it was
right to apply the time of Supply
rules because in so far as the real
world transactions were
concerned there was nothing to
disregard because they took place
outside for
fou um now senser claimed back input tax
on the inputs it had received which were
then attributable to the Management
Services it provided to London
Branch but it didn't invoice for those
Services receive payment for them until
after the two had become
backed the question in Sensa was whether
the Commissioners were right that Sensa
had to pay back some of the that some of
the input tax
recovery because those
inputs because the supplies it made to
London Branch were
treated having a thired in group and
therefore
disregarded and so the that Spenser had
received were
attributed not to taxable supplies but
rather to supplies that the F group as a
whole made VI his representative member
some of which were exempt that was the
question um if we could go to please
page
101 101
this is Lord Hutton's judgment um
f says throughout the period between
1987 and 1st of August
1991 pursuant to the agreement between
them spener provided Management Services
the London Branch it is Common Ground
between the parties that regulation 23
of the 19 85 regulations that is now
regulation 90 of the 1995 regulations so
it was Common Ground between the parties
the regulation 23 applied to those
Services um and then his lordship sets
out that regulation um which you also
see looks
familiar and it is very much not common
ground the case before you that it is
right to apply regulation 19 so spena
doesn't help you resolve the issue in
this
case um and my leared friend um mayw
well that the sign sidelined um take you
to other passages in Spen that the
Commissioners say are Authority for the
proposition that the time of Supply rule
in what is now regulation 90 have to be
applied in order to determine when a
supply to
place and you'll see them um Pages 1 145
sorry 104 and
105 are sidelined and
106 but in considering those passages
when you come to them
um I invite you to bear in mind the
following the real world transaction in
spena took place outside of B grou
it was common ground in spensa that
regulation 90 what is now regulation 90
applied um the issue in spensa was very
different it was whether not
withstanding the application of the
timing
rule um the real life transactions
nevertheless remains taxable supplies by
senska to the London Branch such as
senska was entitled be
clear
you're inviting us to note that it's
Common Ground not simply because
arguably something that's common ground
can't give rise to finding Authority but
because it was right that it was common
ground because it was a different
situation it was a different situation
are you saying are you saying spener was
wrong but we needn't worry but the ratio
was wrong but we needn't worry because
it wasn't argued or are you saying the
ratio was right because it was a
different
situation spenco was a very different
situation what I'm saying is the ratio
in spensa does not help you to resolve
the issue before
you what do you say the ratio
is what they decided in
Sensa was that
um it was right when you applied the
timing
being that one had supplies from spener
to the London branch that took place
intra that group because that's when the
invoices and payments were made so even
though spensa actually provided the
Management Services before they became
back grouped you treat those as
Intergroup supplies they were you're
saying what the decision was rather than
what the ratio
was the the ratio
um
the ratio is the
following perhaps the perhaps the
most useful point to
start is to look at the head notes P 9
page
92 sorry
uh I have it y page 92 held um just
about see the margin on its true
construction regulation 23 which is now
regulation 90 required tribunals in the
court to apply the artificial concept
that not withstanding any actual
physical use upon receipt continuous
supply of services would be treated for
that purposes as not having been
supplied until the early of the time
when the payment in respect of the
services was received or when the Supply
issued to bat invo tax
invo
right and then they talk about the input
tax recovery
position but the premise sorry if you
take that as the ratio if you apply that
to our situation why did regulation 90
not require tribunals and courts to
apply the artificial
concept that not
withstanding when the service
were actually physically
provided continuous supplies of services
were to be treated with v per this has
not supplied until in each case there
was a issue of a tax or payment because
in our case
um for that purposes there is no
actual no actual physical use upon
receipt Because the actual physical use
or the actual provision of the services
took place inside a that group and as
we've just seen you disregarded that as
if that took place within a single legal
entity that wasn't the case in senska
well in Sensa the Practical effect of
applying the time of Supply rules as I
understand that all the services
supplied up to the 31st July 1991 in
fact outside of
that by the UK company to the
Swedish were
treated for vat
purposes are supplied
later when the two entities were in the
F and then you apply the consequences of
what that is which is they're
disregarded and therefore um they can't
the input tax has to be ped
back I think your submission to us is
that that was correct on those
facts that
means
that regulation 199
operates where Services were in fact
supplied outside that group to treat
them as if they were supplied inside
that group doesn't work the other way
around if they were in fact suppli
inside of that group regulation 9
is not applied to treat them as if they
were supplied outside that grou is that
right and that's there's
nothing that is your submission that
that I'm I'm I'm I'm not making
submissions on whether sensar is right
or not but I I do say this which is that
um in Sensa Because the actual supplies
were made outside crew nobody was
arguing that those should be disregarded
have no that consequence and so you
apply the timing rules but what is
different in our our case and it's
unsurprising that it's different and
creates different outcomes is that the
actual transactions took place inside of
that
group so you have to treat them as if
they took place you have to disregard
them as if they took place within a
single legal entity they have no bad
consequence and you don't get around to
applying regulation 90 um and that's
what Lord Nolan says in fact he goes
further he says even if you applied a
timing rule because it was a prepayment
in our case was post payment but it was
a prepayment you'd have to refund it
because the real world transaction the
thing that would create the supply to
which you can apply regulation 90 has to
be disregarded treated as never having
taken place and so yes it is a different
analysis it is a different outcome but
it is the right one um and it is right
because it does make a
difference whether something is done the
thing that's actually done is done
inside of that group or outside of AD
group
so I'm not picking you up on this I just
want to be clear you've obviously been
quite rightly thinking on your feet I
think you're saying Spen is right you
first said you didn't have to say it's
right or not they saying it is right but
it's a different situation and the
principle applied to get to the result
in Spencer doesn't apply in our
situation is because the services aren't
supplied or are supplied within the
group is that right the the outcoming
Spen was about input tax recovery which
is very different um
what I
amum what I might say is this um well
just pick you up on that yes the the
actual underlying issue was about input
recovery but it's a necessary step to
get to the input
recovery their Lordships decided that
the supply of services which is the
output
bit is treated by regation 19
predecessor that's taking place inide
even though in the real world it
didn't by the application of the timing
rule yes um it
it where supplies where the real world
transaction takes place at a time when
the supplier and recipient are not
members of the same that group um and a
continuous supply of services um then
for the purpose of Regulation
90 services are supplied on a continuing
basis or continuous basis whatever
however it's phrased
and whatever consequence flows from that
flows from that and I think that is
right but it is not the case that you
apply regulation 90 when the real world
transactions take place the completion
of the supply the completion of the
transaction takes place inside of that
group that is a very different situation
and that's not senser at
all yeah the closest I'm sorry to turn
this into short hands but you're say
saying that sster was right on its fact
but distinguishable on it very very much
distinguishable very very different
facts if let's put it this way if silver
Fleet and
credential had not been members of the
same F group when silver Fleet provided
Investment Management Services to
credential I wouldn't be here making the
same
argument um and and repeating myself but
the
closest my submission one gets to
guidance on the actual issue in this
case is what Lord no has said in th
materials and it's very clear
there as you point out that that is a
different case because there was only
one Supply or undoubtedly it was the
supply of
goods in the real world Goods only were
supplied on one day and
and the time of supply rules didn't
change that in that case but in our case
the services were supplied over the
period and the time of Supply
rules
do recognize that services are supplied
continuously and the time of Supply
bus say where you've got continuous
supplies you you have separate
supplies separate and successive
suppes and they're determined by when
you when you make pay
that seems a very artificial thing to do
but that's what regulation 9 does so
it's not the
same with the situation posited by Lord
m in Thorne on page
where what he's positing is is a single
Supply on a particular day this is
regulation 9 operates in a slightly
different
way it's different but not in a relevant
way um what is important is that all the
perform the entire it is true that the
Investment Management Services were
performed over a period of time but that
entire period fell within a period when
silver Fleet and credential were V
grouped so everything that was done in
real life was done inside the V group so
there's no relevant distinction from
saying that single transfer of ownership
in Goods took place inside of that
group everything in real life that was
done was done inside of that
group does that mean that if this is
slightly picking up a question my Lord
asked
earlier if silver
fleets carried on supplying Investment
Management Services maybe for a short
time a matter of days or weeks after the
management buy it and after it ceased to
be in the
v and the case would be entirely
different because where the supply of
services straddled both inside the group
and outside the group you could only
determine how much of the consideration
was bable by looking
at the time of Supply rules which not
only tells you when supplies take place
but how
much the consideration is is vable on
each
occasion my Lord you look at the reality
you say in so far as the actual
transactions took place when silver
Fleet and credential were V grouped you
disregard that that's a nullity has no B
consequence if then silver Fleet after
it left the bat group continued to
provide Investment Management Services
for however long that may have been then
that is not dis regarded at least not
under the V grouping rules so that is a
situation where services are supplied on
a continuing basis Etc and you apply
regulation 90 to those supplies and that
creates whatever outcome whatever that
consequence it may create but
nevertheless you disregard everything
that's taking place while silver Fleet
and credential were V grouped what we've
got on the facts of this case is we have
two types of
payment to Silver Fleet One is ongoing
annual management fees which are paid as
when the management takes
place but the other are performance fees
performance fees obviously only get paid
at the back end and everybody knew they
were going to be paid at the back end
because you can only then measure the
performance so in the case I posited
where the investment management
straddled to leave in the group how
would you attribute those performance
fees to intr group group services and
outside group Services you could only do
it by applying the time of Supply rules
couldn't
you well with respect I don't think that
is the case um you you would have
performance fees um bear in mind first
of all that when silver Fleet left the
rat group um a great deal of
um contractual complex contractual
Arrangements were entered into to
provide for ongoing supplies how they
were going to be paid for ETC um so
we're rather speculating that the same
agreement would have covered the ingroup
period and the postgroup period if I put
it that way um but even speculating that
the same agreement would have covered
that
which on the facts um seems unlikely
given given in reality what happened
when silver Fleet left and the number of
agreements that that generated
um it would be for the parties and
failing agreement the court to find a
way
of reasonably and rationally
apportioning the performance fees
to supplies that um are supplies that
are not to be disregarded
and that's not an exercise
um that will be strange to the courts
um but the
the it's all speculation but the reality
May well have been given the parties
involved in what happened in reality
that such a situation would have been
provided for so just just pursuing your
logic a moment the logic is that where
you have a
supply transaction Supply a service
straddling the Dem
merger you then have to work out the
extent to which the consideration is
attributable to postd merger Supply
because on your thesis everything de
pre- demerger is to be
disregarded indeed everything everything
predd merges disregarded it's it's as if
um um we going back to my example where
you have a single legal entity of
different
divisions it might demerge into
two um separate legal entities two
separate companies um one continues to
supply services to the other um there
would be and and and receives
consideration for it there would be a
way to
determine how much of that
consideration is for the supply made
after the
demerger and would we get any help on
that from any statutary provision or
regulation um
if you bear with me my Lord I will have
a think over the short
Jour you were saying um that in a case
where saying in the case that kind were
putting to you you'd ultimately have to
do a rational apportionment and you say
that's case that courts sometimes have
to do you said in fact the parties could
do
it but the courts would do it by default
if they couldn't agree is that the
correct analysis from a tax point of
view
the parties couldn't agree
anything or rather anything parties do
wouldn't be
determinative it would be there would be
an there would for your system to work
conceptually there would have to be an
objective right
answer uh which the Commissioners would
take a view on and if uh you didn't like
that the party who didn't like it would
have to appeal to the courts you're
right my da it's um my apologies um that
the parties may agree
um that certain amount of the
consideration is a portion to the post
group supplies but the Commissioners may
take a different view um and and in that
case yes it would would for to be
determined by triun
Court thank you well you'll come back to
my my Lord's question after the short
which is fine better not to do these
things on who who don't know the answer
yeah um
so still still still in spensa
um just two more things um to note um
first BJ rice which we will come on to
but it was it was
um it was cited to the court um but
nothing said about it my Commissioners
make the point that PJ rice has been um
um you need to limit what you can take
on BJ but um page 92 of Tab 8 um see it
it was CED it was cited but nothing is
said about
BJ also Sensa was decided in 1999 so
that's that's before um commissioner
nand and the rentier and Taylor Clark
and L's banking those
cases
do you say that it would or should have
been different had those cases already
been decided I'm not sure what the no
I'm I'm not saying that my Lord I'm I'm
simply saying that um
whatever point the Commissioners may
make about um Sensa being Authority for
um a certain outcome which is you don't
disregard the in group Supply you apply
the time of Supply rules you have a that
consequence
um I invite you to bear in mind that um
you now have the guidance of commission
Ireland and lentia which says you
disregard Intergroup transactions they
have no
consequence
um quick look um if I may at page 105 so
we're still in Sensa we're still in tab
eight it's page
um again this is a bit that um the
Commissioners rely on um it's it's the
first three paragraphs so a through to
just above D um if perhaps I could just
invite you to read those paragraphs
yourself sorry which page um page
105 and it's the three paragraphs at the
top
yes so when you come to look at that um
again um part of the commission
certainly in the skeleton argument
um bear remind the argument um of Mr mil
in that case um last part of the
paragraph the first paragraph is that
the regulation the timing regulation did
not prevent the services in fact
supplied by Sensa to the London Branch
prior to the 1st of August 1991 being
taxable Supply so it's a very different
argument Mr mil was trying to
argue that the deemed supplies under
regulation
90 which were treated as made intr group
um ought to remain taxable
supplies if the real world transaction
giving rise to them occurred at the time
when the supply would have been taxable
that's the point that was being
argued and that's not the argument in
our case so anything that Lord Hutton
says um is directed to that argument
which is not ours um we say that
regulation 90 cannot impose a v charge
it can't create a taxable
Supply whereas the matter of fact when
the underlying transactions took place
um it took place inside a
background
um and then the commissioner say um
skeleton argument paragraph
25 um I don't know if you want me to
take you to it but um it's for your for
your notes it's in the core bundle uh
Tab four page
61 they say that Lord Nolan's
observation
um in Thor
materials related to the consequence of
applying the disregard but not to
whether or not the disregard
applied not sure understand this if we
look back at Lord Nolan sorry to jump
back into Thor materials but
um it's tab seven of the authorities on
page
sorry we will but short this is the
point you made you yourself made to us
on my
Miss is maybe maybe Mr mantle is using a
slightly different word to describe
it it's not about the consequence it's
about whether um the timing provision
applies at all uh oh I see well okay
sorry I jumped in maybe I misunderstood
where you're going y keep going with
your submission the disregard apologies
the disregard um quick Point perhaps I'm
where are weed but we're in tab seven
age 80
yes is the so I see the particular
passage that we've been focusing on
exactly I'm simply meeting the
commissioner's um point that what Lord
Nolan says there um relates to the
consequence of applying the disregard um
but not whether or not it applies um but
quite clearly you can see Lord Nolan
says um the transfer of ownership in the
goods and thus their supply would you
have taken place but this would have to
be disregarded under Section 29 Etc so
he he is talking about whether you apply
the disregard and the answer is yes you
do so it's not merely about the
consequence of applying it which is what
the commissioner
say
now um I'm I'm about to move on to BJ
rice know about 10 minutes for short
adjournment um would your Lordships like
to write now or should I unless you want
us to for some particular reason I think
it's easier just to stick to the we
don't we may not be able to finish
everything you have say about BJ rice in
10 minutes but we'll certainly be able
to get into it um so BJ rice um now this
this is um moving on in my argument so
we have been talking about why
regulation 90 doesn't apply to all
because you disregard the ingal
transactions assuming that I'm wrong and
you do apply to regulation
19 um that
nevertheless what it can't do is create
a taxable Supply something that is
taxable on Silver
feet and to the extent that um the
commission is saying the skeleton
argument um that we accept that if
regulation 90 applies then lose um
that's not the
case um so BJ rice is in the authority
bundle behind tab
six
page 62 perhaps if I might invite your
lordship to read the the head note all
the way through to um top of page 63 to
yourself well we will if you want us to
but I think it's not it's not
complicated well it's not complicated
they take quite a long time to
read read but the truth is we've all
looked at BJ rice it's been it's at the
center of of your submissions and
therefore of our preading but we'll
quickly read through yeah just remind
ourselves is it any more complicated
than that the taxpayer supplied services
for 150s at a time when he would not
be didn't have to be Ro off is a bad
debt later received payment
of50 when he was V reg that it that's
essentially it we need any more than
that need more than that um commissioner
said in that case that um um uh because
payment was only received after he
became registered that's when you treat
the supplies having occurred and
therefore taxable well in that case
emboldened by not to read the head note
that's what we've all understood I'm not
sure we' all been able to put it so so
Sly so then on page
64 um this is in the Judgment of Lord
Justice ston um
my
apologies
um we set out the um relevant Provisions
section two sub one of the 1983 act this
is the charge to
tax um and then he says this I'm reading
from um just about little e in the
margin um it is said as far as I can see
correctly that there are four elements
in that
subsection there must be one a supply of
goods or services in the Kingdom two
which is a taxable Supply in other words
not exempt three by a taxable person
someone who is or ought to be registered
for that and for in the course or
furtherance of any business carried on
by him it is not disputed that elements
1 two and four were fulfilled when Mr
rice did work for Mr Partridge at some
point before 21st October 1986 but
element three was not Mr rice was not a
Tex person
um and then the answer of the
Commissioners um is by reference to the
timing provision what was then
regulation
23 and then just below little H um his
lordship knows as common ground um that
the work done came within the
description provided by that regulation
notice is not altogether clear to me why
that should be the case but so it is
um and the commissioner's argument in BJ
Rise um is in fact their argument in in
in this case um but over the page on
Page 6
five can see paragraph beginning B in
the margin commission conclude supplies
in this case to be treated as occurring
in point of time when Mr Rice's bill was
paid in March
1991 in know issued a tax invoice it
says at the time the bill was paid Mr
rise was registered and say the
Commissioners fulfill the requirement in
section 2 Sub one that he was a taxable
person at the
relevant um if that is the right
interpretation of the 198 3 act it
produces an unjust result either Mr rice
will be unable to cover recover the tax
from his customer will have to pay it
out of his own pocket or else Mr
Partridge the customer will have to pay
tax although it was not chargeable at
the time when he both contracted for and
received the services of Mr rice um and
and and that's the case here in in BJ
rice if payment has been made at the
time the services were contracted for or
paid or or um or performed there would
be no tax because the time Supply rule
would
say Supply is treated as made at a time
when Mr R was not a taxal
person same situation here when the
Investment Management Services were
contracted for and in fact performed by
silver
Fe if that had been the time of Supply
um no
that undoubtedly no B because they are
within the same B group so a fleet and
credential
um
suppose
a client in Mr Rice's
case contracted at a time when Mr rice
was not vat
registered but you could see that um
payment was not going to be due until
the next tax year next B year and Mr
rice told him that it was Lely that by
the time a vat invoice an invoice was
rendered and
payable his turnover would have
increased to such an extent that he
probably would have to be registered
that make any difference in other words
is it is it the fact that the taxpayer
got the services when Mr rice wasn't
registered which is relevant or that if
he paid the
bill when it was contractually due it
wouldn't he wouldn't have had to pay any
vat that is the determining point as as
we go through the Judgment um it is it
is the former it is that the time of
Supply rules cannot impose
a where none would have been charged at
the time the services were impa supplied
okay thank
you and and then so at the bottom of
page 65 um the last paragraph So I turn
to consider whether regulation 23 fixes
the time for deciding the question of
whether Supply is a taxable person
within section 21 of the 1983 act so
whether the timing provision fixes the
time for deciding whether this charge
the tax at First Sight one would have
thought that it does not surely a person
who is not registered by that for that
because his turnover is below the S
limit should be free to supply goods or
services in The Confident belief that
neither he nor the recipient will have
to bear tax on Supply why else should
there be le of small Traders Etc um and
then one turns um laip says to section
four of the 1983 act um he sets out
section four then he says section five
contains the number of detailed
Provisions as to the time of supply of
goods or services ending with subsection
9 which I've quoted already quoted in
part um then the commissioner's argument
is set out um from Little see through to
um Mr Rice's argument bottom that
paragraph um perhaps if I might invite
your Lordships to read that those two
paragraphs the argument for the
Commissioners and then the next
one
for
and then in the next paragraph beginning
at letter with G um his lordship
acknowledges um f provision in section
41 um and then he says but I would
regard that as a special provision
derogating from section two and that in
all other respects the existence of a
chargeable transaction has to be
determined at a time when the supply is
actually made common sense and Justice
point to that result sections four and
five remain to determine the amount to
be charged and the time when the charge
takes effect to impose the tax charge on
Mr rice in respect of a supply which was
not taxable at the time when it was made
seems to be perilously close to
retrospective
taxation that may have perhaps be
justified
Etc um and then at the bottom of page 66
um so ju just before you go on as Lord
Justice ton has explained Mr Rice's
argument um he has sought to achieve
this result by pointing to the words for
the purposes of the charged attacks in
section
41 um we don't have anything equivalent
in this case well the purpose of the
charge to tax is um in
section six um which is
behind tab one page seven six sub one at
the
end yes I see the same one
yeah um and then at the bottom of page
66 um it's lordship records that Mr rice
sought help from
he says I do however this is last
line on that page I do however find some
assistance in another decision of the
Valle tribunal with the same German
Broadwell land PLC there the tribunal
saiding plain terms it follows from our
analysis so far that the wording of
section four and five do not create any
charge to that those are the timing
Provisions four and five their role is
to identify the time of the supply given
that there has been one which is in
charge under Section 2 Sub one this
conclusion is in line with the opening
words of section 4 sub one which defined
the role of sections four and five as
applying quote for determining the time
when the supply of goods and services to
be treated as taking place for the
purpose of the charge to tax end quote
that's the same wording as what is now
section
six um slice irony there since well
that ston is relying on what Steven
Oliver had said in this other case but
in this particular case he'd arrived at
the opposite
conclusion um but that that had been the
argument the Commissioners um yeah what
he is saying is that um uh it supports
his conclusion that you cannot one
cannot use a timing provision to impose
a tax charge where a tax charge would
not have existed at the time of the the
supply and might that be a convenient
Point yes it would I've just um been
told by the um user that the uh clock is
um 5 minutes behind if it is by stranger
instance it's exactly the same as my
watch which both of which say it's
exactly 1:00 um however we will return
in 1 hour uh which by my watch is 2:00
but if your watch as it's 5 plus one
it'll be 5 plus two I made myself suici
your